welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
okay might as well get going
welcome everybody I see a lot of
familiar faces and names and a few new
ones so that's good I think most of you
are familiar by now with this term that
were kind of exploring called mimetic
mediation or maybe medic diplomacy is
another way to put it
or just give kind of a brief definition
of about how we use it and then we get
into today's activities so so basically
it's the term that that Peter coined a
while back in his article cultural war
2.0 and and basically it just comes from
this acknowledgement that especially
online on the Internet
there's a lot of fractionating mimetic
tribes is is what he called them and
there's a lot of kind of straw Manning
and misunderstanding and dissonance
among them and the idea of mediation is
that well you know if there's gonna be
kind of a networked alternative or this
networked collective intelligence there
needs to be a better way to transmit
information both information and empathy
across these different groups that might
not really understand each other and so
that's that's this idea that we've been
playing with for the last few weeks I
think Peter just posted yeah he posted a
spreadsheet from two years ago where he
mapped out many of these meta tribes and
so if you're interested in that I'm sure
it's evolved and morphed quite a bit
from there and I think we've had about
four or five of these so far and and
basically we they've been different each
time and it seems like we've kind of
gotten into a pattern of having a
session where we
about you know the concept itself a
session where we talk about actual kind
of ideologies you can say or mimetic
tribes that are in tension and talking
about you know how can we facilitate
better dialogue between them we've had
sessions where we do more of an internal
like what is the actual cognitive
dissonance going on inside of you and
how might that be related to perhaps
having multiple kind of conflicting
memes in your own mind right and so it's
connecting it to a more personal level
and then we have sessions with us that's
very meta that's talking about the
process itself so that's kind of the
these are the patterns that we've been
we've been having so far I was thinking
today we could do more of the internal
more of an internal session where and
I'm gonna open it up to everybody pretty
soon we're not gonna have this extended
dialogue Jim Pete Peter and Jared I'll
I'll give you guys a chance to talk to
but I'd like to open it up pretty
quickly but I'd like to if if we can I
just want to give people a space to to
express parts of yourself that feel
conflicted with different ideas or you
know you see messaging from I don't know
from say I'm just gonna give a couple of
examples from from say the techno
utopians for example and it's like and
you see messages from the Eco a pop you
know apocalypse apocalypse seep does oh
my god what is the term anyway you know
what I mean and and there's this rich
tension there where you feel pulled in
both directions and the end doesn't
really make sense so it'd be fun to kind
of get into that today and and really
you know help help each other diagnose
our own internal cognitive dissonance as
related to these kind of external
mimetic movements that are out there I
think last time we did this and it got
more personal like more I feel tension
between being productive and enjoying
life or something like that but this
time
I'd like to connect it explicitly if you
can to these kind of external ideas that
are creating distance within yourself so
if we can kind of occupy that middle
space so not not so personal like you
know my own you know I mean it's all a
continuum how I see it but if we can
kind of occupy that middle space that
would be great I don't know Peter and
Jared before you started you guys have
anything you want to want to bring up
just a desire for me not to talk that
much this time and I really like that
idea of just feeling into the attention
that people are experiencing with
different sort of memes or felt senses I
think that's pretty it pretty
interesting cool Jerry you anything
nothing all right so I want to give the
floor I want to open it up well first
before we before we be open it up in
that way is there anybody who's just
confused or like what the heck are you
talking about let's let's just clear up
any you know if you're confused about
any other terms I use if you're confused
about what I was proposing let's clear
that up right away before we get started
Eko what okay I meant you know so
there's a general there's a general
paradigm that says basically you know
we've gone past our our ecological
thresholds and we're all screwed and
basically humanity's on the pre of
collapse and maybe a few of us survive
if if we get involved with permaculture
and stuff like that and I'm and and and
to be clear I have a foot in that in
that in that camp and that's and I was
just comparing contrasting that to say
more eco eco or techno optimists who say
well you know what solve the climate
crisis and about iversity crisis and all
of these things through technology and
we'll be fine don't worry about it so
maybe like you know the the critical
rationalist David Deutsch Ian's are in
this camp for example so that that was
just an example
all right so anybody like to offer to go
first and maybe I'll just ask one
questions jacent so we're looking for
anybody who has these feeling attention
between 2:00 and themselves or comes
hard comes from one and doesn't
understand the other or is it yeah I
propose the former but but the latter
could work as well so so maybe ok so
let's open this up a little bit so what
seems like we're proposing as an
alternative option is that you know you
generally have a certain sensibility way
of viewing the world and there's another
sensibility that is kind of strange you
don't really understand it maybe a
little bit intriguing you know maybe it
seems a little bit like like there's
really clear blind spots but there's
still something about it that you want
to explore so that's an alternative
option yeah sure ok don't make me call
on people dude do we want to stick
strictly to the list and the spreadsheet
or we don't know it can be it could be
anything that you've identified you can
use a list okay I mean I think within
myself of like maybe say like New
Atheists
and also I have this desire to like go
back and revitalize my like Christian
heritage and there's kind of a tension
there I keep revisiting it and then I
lose interest again and then I gain
interest again and ice I can't I don't
seem to come to a conclusion about it is
it is it is it more the instrumental
components of of the Christian faith
like the the community the ritual or is
there part of belief structure about the
actual claim the Christianity that
you're still you still haven't totally
rejected no I well I think it's more
like I mean I like fully rejected it
pretty much with exception of some some
values but I think I have an interest in
maybe on an emotional level like I feel
like I want to reconnect with it was
such a big part of my upbringing and
every
and I feel like maybe to leave it behind
is almost like leaving behind part of
myself like very emotionally significant
metaphors and I would like he claim them
in some way and yet another part of me
is like gosh there's so much horrific
stuff in the Bible I just don't even
want to have anything to do with it and
so does that make sense
yeah it makes sense to me I don't know
if anybody else has thoughts about that
I guess
one question would be so there's kind of
do you feel feel like you spend more
time in a kind of confused state of how
they relate or a conflicted state in the
way that in the way that they are in
conflict or that they don't match or
something like that I think most of the
time I'm just in the state of ignore it
you know but then I noticed that I go
back to it and then I kind of get more
into the confused state well yeah maybe
maybe I am just in an ongoing condition
you stay and maybe that's correct
saying you were to reject the
metaphysical claims Christianity but but
acknowledge that that religion in
general has evolved it's kind of a you
know it was a cultural evolution and and
a lot of the myths and the ideas
contained a lot of useful information
for for cultural evolution and a lot of
those are still valuable I don't know
what if that statement would resonate
with you at all
definitely resonates yeah yeah I guess
questions like do you do you dig back
into all that tradition and try to
actually like run with it or do you just
kind of keep it as like well yeah out
there I know there is the Bible and
Christianity and like mm-hmm
or you could like go and try to build
community around it and like you know
the integral Christianity if you're
thinking integral theory or whatnot
about anybody else have thoughts about
that I
wanted to say just a lot of what David
just said resonates with me cuz like I
you know my my heritage is Christian and
a lot of my community the people I hold
dear are still very ensconced in that
even system of belief and trying to go
here with that community is is is it big
like that's I very much want to go here
with that the community I have even
though for me like I sense I'm in a
similar place and that I don't accept
that the metaphysical claims but I still
it you know deep in my bones I feel
Christian and so trying to reconcile
those those two things this is quite
interesting I want to think more about
yeah where we're sort of my my where I'm
at with that and how it might connect to
what you've expressed but I just wanted
to say I relate to a lot of that mm-hmm
yeah I just want to jump in quickly
because I was baptized as an Orthodox
Christian and I just deeply resonate
with that tradition I like everything
about it
and and then I'm just like this weird
meta space where just like I'm
just dancing with all these weird memes
and there does feel like a tension there
and it almost feels inauthentic in a way
sometimes but then it feels deeply
authentic just calling it out to so I
have attention with that so for me one
of the interesting things I think I'm
hearing coming up is that the the
tension seems to be largely identified
as a as a kind of uncomfortable kind of
uncertainty of what
connections very very mental a very
mental mismatch and so it's like we're
you know especially as a bunch of
thinkers here we're all could
predominantly looking at things from
kind of a rational perspective and when
we use that rational toolkit to look at
this the religious component of our
lives there's there's like it's just a
complete mismatch it seems in some sense
because we spent so much time rationally
disproving this and yet there's still a
felt kind of emotive embodied quality to
the practice that seems to be that we
don't want to we you know kind of
internally know that there's something
there to hold on to or something like
that
does that sound right ish direction I
would say also story that's a big part
for me mm-hmm what is there a particular
story David and Christianity that
particularly resonates with you I mean I
guess just having the story that someone
sacrificed their life you know for
Humanity is like sounds nice in some way
it feels meaningful to me in some way
that no other more rational system of
thought seems to quite provide I mean
you're just speaking for myself because
I also used to be really just as a part
of the Baha'i faith but kind of I don't
know what I've come to is is that you
know in a way it is it is rational to to
to lean in to these kind of mythologies
you know that we resonate with and it
can be you know that that's a
particularly powerful one you know this
idea of a savior dying for the sins of
humanity and then you know resurrect
like that's that's incredibly powerful
and I know there's like a st. Paul used
like a tree metaphor like a seed
breaking open and then it you know the
tree of the Spirit rising out of it and
it's just like you know that's like
right and and I and I think that I don't
know there's this really delicate place
where you can kind of maintain the
skepticism of any of the metaphysical
claims and one part
you're being but then the other part of
your being kind of like you know you
allow yourself to feel into these
stories that are so rich and I really
you know are really you know have
contributed to how we've gone to where
we are right and I don't know I mean I
personally think we are mythological
creatures right and I don't know if we
can ever get around that even if we
think we can right and so it's how do
you do it in a kind of conscious way or
you know it in a meta if you could say I
met a modern way for me it's like
there's kind of like this sense of sense
of sincerity with it as well as a sense
of kind of ironic distance right and you
can you hold both of those at the same
time yeah and sometimes I wish that I
had just evolved my Christianity rather
than completely breaking with it I feel
like my separating myself somehow it's
hard for me to go back yeah there's a
there's a guy Spears Nathan Spears that
he so we are interviewing a while back
on our podcast but he was raised Baptist
Southern Baptist I believe and many kind
of became atheist agnostic and and and
more recently he's become Orthodox
Orthodox Christian yeah Peter guys are
winning men and he you should he might
be a good person to talk to because he
he has a very kind of nuanced take like
he's very you know he very much occupies
this this liminal space of you know
accepting the claims of that faith but
but in a very in a way that's very non
dogmatic or fundamentalist yeah anyway
maybe maybe looking at you guys yeah
thank you
yeah and I was discussing with Nate
about this he was on your podcast too so
to plug that episode of the both end
podcast with with Nate's BS and then him
and I we both do the Jesus Prayer
I don't do it consistently but it's kind
of like one of their their main
spiritual cycle technologies
technologies where you say this phrase
Lord Jesus Christ son of God have mercy
on me a sinner you just say that mantra
over and over again but you first focus
on the words coming out of your mouth so
you build like a relationship with the
felt sense of the words coming out then
you focus on your mind it like the words
like kind of conjuring up in your mind
then you sink down to your heart and
then so you kind of focus then you start
focusing on all three at the same time
the word coming out of your mouth
their mind and the heart until they
become like sort of fuse together and
when you do this often enough you just
got like you get this crazy so mad
experiences in your body but then the
idea is just have really fused those
three things together so when you speak
you and you think you speak and think
from your heart and then to me if you
can kind of integrate that fully that's
that's Christianity right there mm-hmm
there's a there's a few people putting
some things in the chat Hannah
you you wrote something do you want to
do you want to bring it up or do you
want me to bring it up okay happy to
talk about anything yeah what do you
want you want to read what you wrote and
we can we can respond to that sure I
mentioned that I have the similar
attention within sort of spiritual self
and a rationalist self and I've been
working with that for about two years
now so I feel like I have a pretty good
handle on it but I might be interesting
to others and I was also noting that in
the queer community there is a ton of
discussion on you know people who were
raised within religious tradition had
varying degrees of acceptance of their
identity and
still have this desire to connect with a
tradition whether it's from relation
with the divine or with community or
with with values where there's that
conflict in between the beliefs from
those tradition systems and their
identity and how they can navigate that
tension I'm not personally one of those
people but I do think it's a very rich
area of discussion and then finally I I
found really interesting that the way
Peter describes the Jesus Prayer seemed
in the way I interpreted it to be very
similar to how I do a gratitude practice
you know that connection between sort of
an embodied place of sincerity and
meaningfulness resulting in some sort of
somatic experience that sounded really
familiar thank you
I'd like to chicken please
I hear I hear the phrase the first time
spiritual versus Russia and for me there
is no separation
they married I know what Russian is
really because whatever I think which
makes sense it has values so I believe
in values like my god am i values like
why why are you separate mister I can
speak to that from my own experience I
was just writing about this recently so
it's very fresh on my mind one of the
practices that I do is energy work and
when I started doing it one of the tools
I used to learn it was colored cue cards
I'm touching ones with my eyes closed
to see what sensations arise to me and I
had a lot of resistance to using this
tool to learn the practice and to the
practice itself because the rationalists
tools that I had used to that point to
navigate life with a lot of doubt and
uncertainty from my anxiety held that I
shouldn't be able to sense different
things from different colored cue cards
and I had fears that I wouldn't sense
anything and I had fears that I would
sense things and I would have to change
my beliefs and I had fears that I would
sense things but they wouldn't be
supernatural and that I would have to
accept that two things I saw in contrast
could exist could coexist in the
does that answer your question a little
bit what they hear is that brush you
describe personal as lankan which is
logical and which is not necessarily
something you believe in or something
which is attractive for you I think I
relate to rationale as following in the
spirit of empiricism and the scientific
method and using that to make decisions
when I doubt my own decision-making
[Music]
but you believe in the in this method in
rationalism or energy work in empirical
method I think it is a very useful
technology I don't know if I believe in
it but it's kind of a loaded word for me
maybe I don't know tangential to this
I'm wondering what anybody thinks
rationalism and empiricism it doesn't
presuppose the ability of the human
minds to acquire truth with a capital T
and I don't know what what are the
implications of that is that is that is
that something that I can rationalism
justify that on its on its own merits or
does it does it have to rely on some
kind of some kind of some kind of
foundational belief the thing that
stands out to me about rationalism I
just think of all the branches of
mathematics that require a set of axioms
to start with before you can prove
anything here like rationalism is always
like that you have to have a set of
starting assumptions and so you have to
get those from something non rational
presumably otherwise you you know
rationalist Turtles all the way to here
mm-hmm funny thing they were reporting
that to here is that like one of the
things that there's more religious
sensibility and a more logical or
rational or intellectual sensibility
requires is some sort of leap of faith
tensed trust in in being able to move
forward
and yet they both kind of are based off
of something quite different one of
them's you know quite nebulous and maybe
more symbolic or archaic and then the
other one is more formed patterned and
and logical or sequential or something
like that but yeah they do kind of share
the same quality they're both kind of
being based on a foundation of trust so
if we were to extend this out and you
know as you know as aspiring mimetic
mediators if our goal was to mediate
between Christians or you know some
other religion and and the less wronged
rationalists for example I don't know
where would we where do we start I mean
I know that's already been kind of been
happening I know there's been kind of an
exodus from some of the rationalist
community there's like the post
rationalist what they call them and and
and they're kind of becoming religio
curious again and you know and getting
into mythology and and all of these
things perhaps with you know it's coming
from a different place than a
traditionalist but so it seemed that
seems to me that there's already some
kind of mediation or integration of
where we've come from into where we're
going but I'm wondering if people have
thoughts or thoughts about that the
thing I've been thinking about recently
is how to take like we could take for
example what you mentioned Jason the
rationalist versus Christian if we were
if I were trying to mediate between
those two groups I think my goal would
be to get both sides to see the the role
of the participatory
as more fundamental than the
propositional so so so trying to get
both sides to see this idea that the the
way that we perceive depends upon the
the way in which we are participating in
the world and so I mean for both the
rationalist and the you know believing
Christian there's this idea that truth
with a capital T is you know what
they're like both both I think would
stake their you know would plant their
flag in that that idea of truth with a
capital T but then it seems like neither
one typically recognizes the role that
the process of the process of getting at
truth with the capital T like that's
more fundamental than the the eventual
propositions that you may find there and
how to go about how to go about leading
people into that recognition which I
think it's very important when you
emphasize the process of seeking truth
over the the conclusions that you've you
think that you've already made
well the rationalist might just say well
is the scientific method or the Critical
rationalist would say we're looking for
hard to very explanations right good
good explanations that are hard to bury
meaning that if you could completely
change the story like what David Deutsch
argues is that you could you know among
religions you have completely different
stories
and it kind of it's okay you know in the
grand scheme of things you know but you
know for for a scientists if you have an
explanation and you very significantly
it doesn't make predictions anymore it's
it's it's totally useless and so that
I'm just playing devil's advocate to
what you're saying I'm wondering if you
have thoughts on that yeah just a
question I'm not the last piece that you
mentioned mm-hmm
but I also just wanted to say that I
agree with the way that Joe framed the
question meaning um putting focus on the
process of getting to truth capital T is
an interesting way to put it but
especially when I really like that in
the stoah being a philosophical way of
thinking as well stoicism itself and and
this kind of culture that we've gotten
into where we're speaking from our own
perspectives and seeing truth from our
own sort of perspectives so the capital
T bit is something that I personally
have always wondered how to get to in
our own personal process but with that
said I wanted just clarity on what that
last piece about scientists that you
said was I think I just wasn't paying
attention I was just I was just playing
devil's advocate that so you're talking
about instead of focusing on what is the
correct proposition what is the process
and I was saying well if a hardcore
rations here they might say well the
process is the scientific method so we
already have the process and in each I
was just I was just throwing that out
there as you know how you know how would
somebody how would somebody respond if
they were a mediator or I don't know no
we're not to shut down the conversation
I make sense thank you I really hi
boys because I'm speaking through fears
that's literally what it is which
reminds me of um what Hannah said um
because um I I relate to her talking
about um I see her but you kind of
talking about the energy work that you
participate in
um and seeing and I don't think I paid
full attention to that either but I did
pick up pieces about I'm sensing
something that is been true to you in a
way I'm you can clear you can clarify
that because you know I yesterday and I
like coming from stories too because um
that helps me ground so we castor day I
was part of like a free styling session
and during the free styling session I
brought up the fact that I have like
tarot cards on my desk that I'm trying
to practice and so someone else was also
like hey like I have a nice too but
they're of animal spirits and then so II
freestyled using those cards that
someone else had um so so so with that
said I like the process although I think
that there is value in the scientific
method um there are other processes or
methods that can help with getting to
the truth that people are seeking but I
would also argue that there needs maybe
to be care in the type of actions we're
taking and decisions we're making to
come from like an ethical way of working
for whatever practical thing that you're
working with
[Music]
okay can I jump in here hmm
so one of my one of my questions coming
into all of your sessions is how is the
mimetic mediation different than a
regular mediation and the way that I'm
trained in a regular mediation and they
said this was probably the hardest thing
for me when I was going through the
training coming from like a philosophy
kind of background where there's a lot
of focus on epistemology and knowledge
all my meat-eater teacher said get that
out of here we don't focus on that
at all we only focus on what the
person's underlying values needs
interests and identities are and we get
away from like what truth is and that
saved that for the lawyers and judges in
court and so I don't know if that
framework applies in an emetic mediation
but III do believe what you know what
Peter Bogosian Simon's latest book where
he calls moral epistemology where under
everyone's identity or meme that that
your identity is entangled with there
it's you hold that position because you
think that that makes you a good person
right it is actually ultimately like a
bedrock value or moral issue so my kind
of framework for going into these
conversations whether it's between the
religious person the atheist or
political or whatever is try to drill
down to what the person's values are and
the role that religion whatever plays in
their life and then you can have some
you know you can understand how it's
meaningful to the person or what's
inflow or the how its valuable or or
morally inspiring for you to hold those
positions it's one of the check them
quickly this may be a little bit of a
side but it just sparked when you were
talking that so I have sort of I don't
have a mediation background but I used
to work with mediators and the unions
and I've seen that I see the mediation
is an action and I do think like mimetic
mediation done right if there's stunned
by a person's probably it looks exactly
the same as a regular mediator but I
think the term or the me mimetic
mediation is sort of like a strange
attractor to people who want to mediate
between different people who have
different ideologies mm-hmm yeah I think
you it's a really good point is you know
is the role of a mediator
you know to establish truth with a
capital T or a process of getting at
truth and I'm not sure I mean III think
release for me my interest is really
just just prompting constructive
dialogue you know across these groups
and and whatever you know whatever comes
out of that is it's kind of for me it's
kind of a second-order effect doesn't
really you know as a mediator that's not
really my job is to establish you know
okay we we come to a new set of truths
that then that blends all of it
everybody's truths into one single you
know meta truth that I don't think
that's the role of a mediator I think
it's really just to to help facilitate
to start the process of dialogue right
and it might not even be a truth that
their dialogue and about it's just a
process a relationship building right
where they're they're not you know it's
more about building empathy and and also
be you know developing the capacity to
see other perspectives to Donella
Meadows talks of uses this term collect
mental models and to be able to inhabit
different mental models and you know you
can think of it both as okay in one
sense maybe maybe some better notion of
big t truth will come out book or if not
it's more about just improving
communications so that you can you know
you can collaborate for example in
building a better society right and you
don't actually have to end up ever
agreeing with each other right like
that's not I don't know if that's
necessary right and I'm curious so one
of the things starting to think of some
of the unique qualities or aspects of
the cinematic framing and part of it is
it's like to Jason's point it's a little
bit more long-term thing we're not
there's not any overt focus on
resolution especially in the short term
and the other thing here is that it's
it's more of a cultural orientation
rather than interpersonal I think and
especially since
a lot of these mimetic conversations the
people that would be talking often I
think and I in some of the disagreements
that I see online and stuff is people
feel they're speaking for a tribe rather
than kind of defending their own own
space and so my question to you would be
you know with with the the formal
mediation background how often do you
feel like this is the the mediation is
happening between tribes versus
interpersonally and of course they're
both going to be present in every one of
these exchanges but it seems like the
mimetic war might be more a little bit
more leaning on the tribal element here
I've never done a mediation between
tribes everything is like I want to put
my friends here and now yelling for my
friends here so after you and let's work
out an agreement and sign a contract
super boring that's why I'm here
I want something juicier and more epic
so like thanks for explaining to me I
mean I've kind of been you know locked
into certain framework so I have to do
magnetic mediation between regular
mediation in the minivan
well and one thing as you're talking
right here I think you know the other
unfortunate thing is that the mimetic
tribes because it is a lot of it is
about ideal ideology and philosophy a
lot of these conversations really do end
up in more of the intellectual duals
right or it's not really I'm protecting
my my thing where I want a certain
outcome I'm going to prove the
superiority of my ideas and and Jason as
you were speaking you know we're going
to our hypothetical of the the critical
rationalist versus the or the
rationalist versus the the religious
minded one thing that I thought I think
is important to do especially as a
mediator is to always be kind of
sampling the the emotional disposition
of the conversation and a lot of times
that's like for me it's kind of a
calibrator to know where I need to give
my effort so if so if I wanted it in the
spectrum I'm sensing a lot of hostility
or defensive Mis from somebody I know
I'm probably gonna not I want to push or
attack them direct their directly on and
in in that case I might try and find
some sort of commonality or bring it
back down to a interation inter inter
personal thing to get to build some
empathy and get back into the body and
to kind of you know put you put that
give it a chance to put themselves
another person's shoes or something like
that but if everything's very cool heads
then maybe sometimes this you know we
could go live in the intellectual and we
could say that you know Jason's point
you know maybe the we can say hey
there's a lot of perennial philosophy
people who think the religions do share
an underlying epistemology and they're
just culturally different or something
and then we could get into that we could
stay there but the movement in the
moment that the emotion the triggering
as a Hansie and the meta modernists say
arise I think that there's always a cue
to see if we need to take a step back
and get into the get out of
fight-or-flight mode just mmm few
thoughts
so we think we have about twenty minutes
or so we started about five minutes late
so I figure we can go extra five minutes
or so we can continue along this line of
conversation or if somebody else wants
to give another example of some kind of
internal dissonance you know with
certain ideas or memes ideologies that
that you find that one day you think one
you know you agree with one side the
next day you with the other side and so
there's some interesting tension there I
wonder if anybody else wants to wants to
express you know a case another case
study yeah because you have experience
in mediating in the real world which I
do not this is my first time figuring
out what mediation really means could
you explain what you mean by like fences
and contracts and signing things because
I have no idea what that meant yeah it's
the most boring thing ever
so it's basically like we gotta like
there's a lot of community mediations
between like angry neighbors it's like
one of the most common ones where
they're kind of like property disputes
about like well my property line is here
and you need to and your offense is you
know your tree is growing over my and
into my property and I so I cut down
your branch and then it's like how dare
you cut down my tree you know so it's
very like um oriented towards external
like property and stuff that should be
sorted out probably in like code and not
but but there are a lot of like personal
feelings of anger and animosity between
the neighbors which is usually why they
can't work out the problems themselves
and they have to have a third party
mediator come in but I guess why I find
it boring is because I'd rather explore
you know
or more explicitly the values and
psychological dynamics underneath it
instead of dislike needy trying to have
people reach agreements about like
you're gonna plan you're gonna put this
end of the fence here on July first I've
been I'm gonna call you back in five
days you know it gets very technical
like that and you have to go through
with them and then they sign a contract
so it's pretty bad obviously
[Laughter]
it's super super helpful Thanks yeah
maybe this is a question we could throw
out there as Ryan said we have these
kind of formal mechanisms for legal
mediation to be requested how could we
as mimetic mediators like what cues
could we be taking from the environment
that there's there's mediation that
needs to be happening especially since
this isn't a well-known space at the
time nobody's gonna know that this is a
possibility or that it could take place
or something like that
um yeah I'd be curious to know you know
maybe this is something that we can put
together and even our slack channel to
be like hey I saw this collision on
Twitter or I you know I was in a private
call and this came up or you know you
know because it feels like we have to be
kind of sourcing the opportunities for
mediation differently rather than the
more traditional forms of mediation and
there's so many good comments that are
coming into the chat I'm tempted almost
to to read a couple of them you know
Hanna wrote I wonder how common enemy
strategy factors into medic mediation
and I think I've noticed that that
happens a lot where you know and this
this kind of gets into I think more just
our evolutionarily kind of tribalist
natures of in-group and out-group where
you know if if you can trade with
somebody or you can collaborate with
them effectively to defeat an external
enemy then then you will and your put
ideal ideology aside so there's a
certain pragmatism there and maybe Ryan
that's what you were talking your
just Rihanna as well with the fence and
the contracts of like you know this kind
of there's this pragmatic solution
that's not actually getting at the core
kind of psychodynamics of it but and I'm
wondering a nomadic mediation if we
could draw in this relate of the David's
comment as well if we can kind of draw
analogy to a mimetic mediation where you
know when when is the time to get into
the you know core underlying
psychodynamics you know build empathy
you know familiarity with Chile
worldview and when is the time just to
be pragmatic and you know just let's
just stop you know let's just stop
warring with each other right because
it's just creating this kind of cultural
dissonance that's not good for anybody
and so can we just come up with a
pragmatic solution and I'm wondering if
there's a spectrum there and you know if
both have their place we'll think about
that think about that probably not the
only way to frame it but that sort of
pragmatic solution oriented focus may
one tool that the facilitator and the
mediator might use I could see other
situations where that that wouldn't be
helpful or that wouldn't be the best way
to keep the process flowing but I really
like I really like the question of what
is a mediator period versus what is a
memetic mediator you know if the goal is
to create consensus that seems like kind
of a losing battle in this postmodern in
post-postmodern world were in so you
know what are we doing exactly if we're
not trying to create consensus and you
said something along the lines of having
generative conversations and yeah I'm
curious about all the other things that
a memetic mediator could be doing in
terms of sort of like goals like if they
were the mimetic mediator stepped into a
conversation what would their what would
their goals be if they had to articulate
them
mm-hmm I think I mean I think somebody
somebody to mention you know or you
mentioned you know having a generative
conversation so it's for me it's not so
much like okay you're gonna agree with
each other and then become the same
tribe like that could happen but that
doesn't that doesn't necessarily need to
happen I think is it's just more
facilitating a process of perspective
taking and that could be a more of a
formal process or an informal process
but it's perspective taking and and and
kind of you know encouraging people to
to at least try and empathize the other
point of view and to imagine yourself
taking on the other point of view and
you know what would the world like look
like then and so it's it's more like
just enabling interaction that in a
command there can be a lot of tension
you know but I like this term generative
tension right but it's actually
generating something that that is
positive for the larger culture you know
and we can talk about what positive
collateral means as well that would be
my answer at least and the first thing
that came to me is like I remember for a
while my brother and I I was staying at
his house and he kind of has we were
just completely opposite ideologically
but for this one trip for whatever
reason we had a bunch of kind of
fighting arguments and telling white
each other why each other was stupid and
yet there was still kind of this
conviviality and and we left each of
those conversations kind of feeling like
yeah I got to work out my ideas and test
them and and we it was not it didn't you
didn't leave feeling like it was some
sort of destructive exchange it was
actually generative to Jason's point and
yeah but the more that those
conversations are are enabled in the the
broader cultural wars I think the more
we'll able to be able to actually
collectively grow as opposed to
individually wither
conviviality is such a good word if
we're sowing the seeds of conviviality
hmm that's a great that's a great phrase
I got to give it to Jim rut is the one
that got one that would entice them to
it was Ivan Illich for me mm-hmm yeah I
kind of these different levels where you
know in kind of what you're speaking
with Jared there's one level where
you're not even trying to come to terms
on a similar worldview you're just
building a relationship right and so
it's like you know if if you're just not
gonna not gonna be able to have a
conversation about how you see the world
you know have a conversation about you
know a band that you both like right and
your love for some shared thing and it
can be completely sub ideological and
you know for me like that's of benefit
in itself with a large larger benefit is
you know when something does flare up
and kind of this cultural tension you'll
be less likely to attack that other
person if you just have a you know just
a very normal you know really sub
ideological relationship with them
you'll be less likely to at least attack
them right and to hear them out hmm
let's see Hannah do you wanna use it a
couple I haven't read it exactly
everything you've said but how do you
want to do you want to talk about what
your being up here I think what you just
described is a tool that I use all the
time and I think it's a really useful
survival tool for minorities you know if
you are going to be disagreed with at
every turn in terms of who you are what
you believe then often the most peaceful
thing is to just change the subject in
order to get what you need
I think that is not a new idea but
perhaps describing it or bringing it to
light is useful yeah do you I mean in
one sense I mean - I mean it's a
survival tool I mean it's unfortunate
that it has to be a survival tool right
like there's the the you know it seems
like you're kind of bringing up you know
these notions of kind of power
asymmetries you know between
interlocutors which might force one side
to to have to adopt the you know a
survival tool you know like this whereas
the other side doesn't have to drop
survival in that and that's one thing I
don't think we've really discussed in
any of these pneumatic mediation chats
is how do you account for it for the
power asymmetries within the you know
interlocutors where one person one side
you know has to be much more agreeable
because you know their their bottom line
you know there's their survivability is
much more at stake and this is a whole I
think this is a conversation for a whole
session personally but just just
throwing it out there yeah I think
[Music]
having the tools to actually describe
that that survival mechanism you might
call it might be empowering for people
if you're able to use it on purpose
mm-hmm so yeah I agree
you could you could go into this at
length yeah I think it would be an
interesting conversation in the future
as well I often think about perception
and action as these sort of opposites
that are deeply interconnected and
mutually defining and then what you just
said made me think what if power was
kind of a third leg on that what would
that look like if action perception and
power related in some kind of
fundamental way and
I have to think about that more yeah me
too yeah and where we have about five
more minutes I'm wondering if anybody
has any you know I just want to give the
space for anybody has last thoughts
about what we've been discussing or you
know any other stray thoughts that
you've been itching to get out before
you wrap up I just had the question of
who's gonna mediate among the mimetic
mediators as they're trying to define
what that is yeah go ahead dude III have
something to say about that but I always
say to myself go ahead good that rule
feels alive for me and it Jason Jason
and Peter just are in the process of
releasing some some articles on mimetic
mediation and the two of them kind of
have very different takes at least in
these things I haven't read them both
yet so I'm excited to do so but but yeah
I've already I'm already thinking about
how could I mediate these two so I would
love to be in that role
mediation is the role you find yourself
in when your siblings are fighting so I
Ryan did you have were you gonna raise
their hand I was just joking saying that
I'm down to maybe Jared and I can do a
cool mediation between Jason and let
Peter me and Peter aren't talking right
now it's just really bad you know we're
just talking past each other most of the
time ya know
well I I guess how how I've been thing
about that is I see it kind of fractal
in the sense where I think all mediators
like everyone in in some small domain or
a large domain of their life is
mediating but everyone is also being
mediated right so and it can kind of go
up and down the stack so I could be
mediating people who are mediating
someone else remaining someone else but
then those last that last person of a
chain might be me aiding me right as a
you know
day I'm like head mediator but then the
next day you know I need to be mediated
with another mediator and so I see one
of the benefits of a community of
mediators is that we're constantly
meeting each other all the time
right and so it's it's not like one
person mediating the mediators but then
who mediates them and you know the
turtle is all the way up type of thing
but it's it's this kind of web of Co
mediation where you know we're always
gently you know trying to call out each
other's blind spots you know and it's
like okay when I saw you mediating that
tribe your bias was showing or I noticed
a bias you know and say you're gently
pointing that out you know in the next
week that same person who said that to
me I might notice that then when someone
else and hopefully I'm not just doing
that because I'm taking revenge but you
know so it does require some you know
reflexivity and and contemplative
maturity I would say and I think Jason
had much more foresight in wisdom than I
did here cuz I'm like I approach this
thing really cautiously
I got some but we gotta get all done
like the technology the ideas down and
this guy's like a cowboy just hey we
have a slack Ruby just vice everyone in
there or just like him both throwing
elbows but I think he's he's right
definitely I think Jason's right is that
it's like in order to become good medic
meters we got to practice with each
other's like a dojo and we model it for
each other we see it being modeled or
inspired by it just the fact that we're
all attracted to this mean to some
extent I think it's you know half the
battle is already won there speaking of
getting in the mess of it so as we were
talking about identifying where
mediation it needs to take place I think
David mentioned that one of the kind of
primary battlegrounds right now seems
like it's Twitter I wonder if I if I
would it it could invite everybody to
use a hashtag or something or a phrase
on Twitter
Twitter exchanges that seem like
mediation is needed or or is happening
that might be never give us some more
real-world mimetic content to to go over
in this this call even especially if
we're doing it in public if anybody's
willing to do it I I mean I do it all
the time I just never labeled it so I
guess it would be interesting to kind of
start pushing that out into the broader
webs all right well thank you everybody
I think I think we'll wrap up now as
somebody posted on the on the chat we do
have a slack group and mimetic mediation
slap group and there's many channels
that have conversations there's also
within the slack group there's a
mediation campfire channel which we can
have conversations that we want to
continue from from these you know audio
these video calls so feel free to get
involved with that if you like and yeah
and also you know if you have
suggestions for for future we do this
every week so if you have suggestions on
kind of what approach to take because
every every time seems to be quite
different please let us know as well
because it's you know we're just I see
this as like we're all just kind of Co
discovering this attractor point that
seems to be rich for some reason right I
just wanted to jump in briefly so we're
rotating on mostly three of us so Jared
gets next week but if anyone like the
regular sugar called to run it like rain
or Ryan or whoever like you know feel
free to suggest them we can take you in
and I also just wanted to plug the side
view is launching their latest episode
on Wednesday and then Jason and I the
reason why we're not talking to each
other is that we released two separate
mimetic mediation pieces that were
supposed to be one piece but we couldn't
even make it happen
but those are being released and then
we're having a launch party on Wednesday
at the Stowe as well as we go on the
store that's a two hours to give you
that thanks Peter
thanks Jason yeah thanks thanks everyone
take care of see you next week hopefully
alright thank you so much thank you